Guide to the Papers of Robert Ross Alden,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Robert Ross Alden Papers,
1935-1973
Alden, Robert Ross.
10 linear ft (20 boxes and 1 oversize folder).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
MS#0014
4078413
Biographical Note
Robert Ross Alden, 1922-1973, (born Robert A. Rosenfeld) began working at the New York Times in 1941 as a messenger boy while he was still an undergraduate at City College. Except for his army service during World War II, his entire career was spent at the Times in a wide variety of positions including local reporter; war, diplomatic, and Southeast Asia correspondent; director of real estate news; assistant metropolitan editor; and at his death, United Nations Bureau Chief.
Scope and Content
Professional and personal papers containing correspondence, manuscripts (chiefly typescript versions, many with holograph corrections), documents, photographs, memorabilia, newspapers clippings, printed materials, and some art work. The letters cover his professional, personal and family life. Among the significant correspondents are Orvil E. Dryfoos, James B. Reston and the Sulzberger family. The majority of the papers consist of Alden's manuscripts for his articles and editorials written for the "New York Times." There are some articles that were submitted to various magazines, as well as copy under the pseudonym, Carlton (Tubby) Belmont, written for the Women's news Service. Alden's "Times" writings deal with the New York metropolitan area, the 1963-64 World's Fair, France, Cuba, Southeast Asia, Ships, and the United Nations. In addition there are manuscripts of his stories, novels and poetry. The stories and novels deal with reporters, politics, war and show business. Alden's personal papers and documents relate to his years at City College and in the Army and contain other personal items. Also included is a typescript copy of his autobiography. The newspaper clippings and printed matrerials are mostly of his writings. There are numerous photographs as well as more than one box of memorabilia.
The letters cover his professional, personal and family life. Among the significant correspondents are Orvil E. Dryfoos, James B. Reston and the Sulzberger family. The majority of the papers consist of Alden's manuscripts for his articles and editorials written for The New York Times.
There are some articles that were submitted to various magazines, as well as copy under the pseudonym, Carlton (Tubby) Belmont, written for the Women's News Service. Alden's Times writings deal with the New York metropolitan area, the 1963-64 World's Fair, France, Cuba, Southeast Asia, Ships, and the United Nations. In addition there are manuscripts of his stories, novels and poetry.
The stories and novels deal with reporters, politics, war and show business. Alden's personal papers and documents relate to his years at City College and in the army and contain other personal items.
Also included is a typescript copy of his autobiography. The newspaper clippings and printed matrerials are mostly of his writings. There are numerous photographs as well as more than one box of memorabilia.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 10 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Arranged Correspondence
Series III: Manuscripts
Subseries III.1: Articles for Periodicals
Subseries III.2: Novels
Subseris III.3: Stories
Series IV: Personal Papers and Documents
Series V: Manuscripts
Series VI: Memorabilia
Series VII: Photographs
Series VIII: Printed Materials
Subseries VIII.1: Magazines
Subseries VIII.2: Newspaper Clippings
Series IX: Scrapbooks
Series X: Art Work
Subjects
Dryfoos, Orvil E.; Reston, James, 1909-1995.; Sulzberger, Arthur Hays, 1891-1968.; Sulzberger, Arthur Ochs.; Sulzberger, Iphigene Ochs.; New York (N.Y.); Photoprints; Journalists; New York times.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1977 Papers Alden, Dion Gift
Gift of Dion Alden (Mrs. Robert), 1977.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  Arranged alphabetically
  - Brooks, Gladys Rice Billings (Mrs. Van Wyck) (Box 1)
  - Crowther, Bosley (Box 1)
  - Dryfoos, Orvil E. (Box 1)
  - Farago, Ladislas (Box 1)
  - Heubsch, Ben W. (Box 1)
  - Kennedy, John Fitzgerald Certificate (Box 1)
  - Levine, Joseph E. (Box 1)
  - Lindsay, John Vliet (Box 1)
  - Lynes, Russell (Box 1)
  - Mancroft, Stormont, 2nd Baron (Box 1)
  - Reston, James Barrett (Box 1)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson Aldrich (Box 1)
  - Romulo, Carlos P. (Box 1)
  - Sinclair, Upton (Box 1)
  - Steinhem, Gloria (Box 1)
  - Sulzberger, Arthur Hays (Box 1)
  - Sulzberger, Arthur Ochs (Box 1)
  - Sulzberger, Iphigene Ochs (Mrs. Arthur H.) (Box 1)
  - Waldheim, Kurt (Box 1)
  - A-G (Box 1)
- Series II: Arranged Correspondence
  - H-Z, Unidentified correspondence, Family correspondence (Box 2)
  - Letters of Condolence (Box 3)
    [These letters are unfolded, most still in their original envelopes]
- Series III: Manuscripts
  - Subseries III.1: Articles for Periodicals
    - General: chiefly New York City Metropolitan Area (Box 4)
    - Writings about various countries in Asia, Cuba and France. Also, related research materials. (Box 5)
    - Ships, Talent, Topics of the Times, United Nations. (Box 6)
    - United Nations (Box 7)
    - Articles written under the Carlton (Tubby) Belmont, pseud., Incomplete articles, Related materials to several stories, Editorials, Miscellaneous, Poetry, Novels (Box 8)
  - Subseries III.2: Novels
    - "The George Duck Story" and "World of Vietnam". Drafts and corrected typescripts (Box 9)
  - Subseris III.3: Stories
    - Stories (Box 10)
- Series IV: Personal Papers and Documents
  - Address and date books; Army documents; Biographical materials; City College papers; and Personal documents. (Box 11)
- Series V: Manuscripts
  - Alden, Robert Ross Autobiography. (Box 12)
- Series VI: Memorabilia
  - Memorabilia, including Signma Delta Chi Award, Award plaques, Press badges and cards, Pins and Army decorations. (Box 13)
- Series VII: Photographs
  - Photographs, related to his stories written for the New York Times. (Box 14)
    [Photographs are in no order and need rehousing. ]
- Series VIII: Printed Materials
  - Sunseries VIII.1: Magazines
    - Printed materials of NY Times Magazine, US News and World Report, and several other publications that featured articles by Alden. (Box 14)
      [No order present and the paper is in need of preservation. ]
    - Magazines with articles by Alden, reprints of individual pieces, and a number of "Times Talk", an internal publication for the staff of the New York Times. 1950s-1960s (Box 15)
    - United Nations related items, such as memos, and a large number of invitations to official events. (Box 16)
  - Subseries VIII.2: Newspaper clippings
    Arranged chronologically
    - 1952-1958 (Box 17)
      [Original clippings need preservation work. ]
    - 1959-1965 (Box 18)
    - Unsorted (Box 19)
    - Unsorted (Box 20)
- Series IX: Scrapbooks
  - Nos. 1 & 2, contains clippings of Alden's newspaper pieces, No. 1: 1 March 1947 - 22 August 1951, No. 2: 5 Jan. -31 Dec. 1960 (Box 21)
  - No. 3, contains clippings of Alden's newspaper pieces, 1 January - 9 July 1961 (Box 21)
  - No. 4, contains clippings of Alden's newspaper pieces, 25 March 1972 - 23 October 1973 (Box 116)
  - No. 5: World's Fair and No. 6: World's Fair, contains clippings of Alden's newspaper pieces, 1963 - 1964 (Box 115)
- Series X: Art Work
  - 1. Pencil sketch of Robert Alden, 2. Two unidentified pencil sketches, 3. architectural pen-and-ink sketch by De Scutt, 1970 (Box 2)